[MUSIC PLAYING]
How you doing today, sir?
Hi.
Can I see your license and registration please?
What was I doing?
Speeding.
I was?
Yes, you were.
How do you know I was speeding?
You're looking a little tired.
How long you've driving today?
Maybe two hours.
We did you come from?
New Jersey.
How far away is New Jersey?
170 miles.
So 170 miles divided by 2 is 85 miles an hour, sir.
Isn't that a little fast?
OK.
So you knew my average speed was 85,
but how do you know there was an incident when
I was traveling at 85?
Sir, it's simple math.
The mean value theorem states that one moment
your instantaneous speed is going
to match your average speed.
You got me.
OK.
Can I have that license and registration now, sir?