Here is the conclusion of the mean value theorem
that we have already seen.
There is some point c, between and b, at which the tangent is
parallel to the secant.
You have just seen that this statement
holds for some functions, but doesn't for some others.
So what are conditions that will guarantee
that the MVT conclusion holds?
Let us investigate the examples from the problem you just
solved.
We have collected the successful functions,
the ones for which the MVT conclusion hold,
on the top row, and the failures,
on the bottom two rows.
We will start by discussing why the functions in the middle row
fail.
Let us look at the first graph.
For the first graph, we can shift the secant line
to approach a point where it is tangent to our graph.
But we find that the exact point that this would have happened
is a point where the function is undefined.
So there is no c.
Next, let's look at the second graph in the middle row.
It has a jump discontinuity at an endpoint.
The secant line slants down, but all the tangent lines slant up,
so there is no c.
Because of the discontinuity, there
is no relationship between the slope of the secant
and the slope of the tangents.
Similarly, for the rest of the graphs in this row,
the reason that the MVT conclusion fails
is a discontinuity either at an endpoint
or within the interval.
Let's look at the bottom row now.
Each of these two graphs is continuous
but has a point within the interval where
the derivative does not exist.
In the first, there is a corner, and in the second,
there is a cusp.
You can check that the reason there
is no tangent parallel to the secant
is because of the point where the function is not
differentiable.
Let us now look at the successful functions.
We can use the same method as before
to find a point at which the tangent is parallel
to the secant.
We see that the first four graphs on this row
have hump shapes at whose peaks the c's appear.
On the other hand, the last function on this row
is equal to the secant line, so at every point,
the tangent is also equal to the secant line.
In other words, every point within the interval is a c.
What do all these graphs have in common?
Well, all of these graphs are continuous and differentiable.
Let's return to our question, what condition on a function
will guarantee that the MVT conclusion holds?
We already see that continuity and differentiability
are conditions that will include all
of our examples of successes, and exclude
all of our cases of failures.
It turns out that continuity and differentiability are
enough to guarantee success.
So let us state the mean value theorem precisely.
If a function x of t is continuous
on the closed interval a to b, and
differentiable on the open interval a to b,
then there is some point c in the open interval
a to b such that the average rate of change from a to b
is equal to the instantaneous rate of change at c.
Let's write this conclusion in terms of formulas
now rather than words.
The average rate of change from a to b
is equal to x of b minus x of a, divided by b minus a.
And the instantaneous rate of change
at c is equal to x prime of c.
Notice in the hypothesis the function
needs to be continuous on the closed interval, including
the endpoints, but needs to be differentiable only
on the open interval.
So the derivative does not have to exist for the endpoints.
Let us now do some exercises.
And we will continue with some immediate consequences
of the MVT.