In this sequence, we'll be developing ways
to use the derivative of a function, f,
to get information about the shape of the graph of f.
For instance, we know that if f prime
is positive on interval a comma b,
then f is going to be increasing on that interval.
And if f prime is negative between a and b,
then f is decreasing on that interval.
We've seen this before.
But let's use this to figure out some things about the graph.
So for instance, maybe f of x is the function 1 plus
4x minus x cubed over 3.
And here, f prime of x is 4 minus x squared.
And we can tell when this is positive
and when it's negative.
The derivative is positive when x squared is less than 4.
And that happens when x is between 2 and minus 2,
so on the interval minus 2 to 2.
And the derivative is negative when
x squared is greater than 4.
So that's on the intervals from minus infinity to minus 2
and from 2 to infinity.
So between x equals minus 2 and x equals plus 2,
f is going to be increasing.
So its graph will look something like this.
Whereas, to the left of minus 2, the graph will be decreasing,
and also to the right of plus 2.
So there we have it.
Now, this doesn't tell us everything
we might want to know about the graph.
We don't know where it crosses the x-axis.
We don't know how high this point is,
or this point where the graph turns around, in other words.
But those things we can get with algebra.
The calculus does give us a good sense of the overall shape
of the graph.
And that's definitely useful.
As we go forward, we're going to develop more and more language
which we can use to describe various features of graphs.
And for each of them, we'll see how calculus
can be used to find them.
Sound good?